You're here, Bob, of course. Bob is hot. Bob is very hot.
Welcome to BSD is Dying.
No, it's not dead yet,
we're getting there.
Anybody out here last year?
Okay. I gave a really bad talk on pf, and I
appreciate Bob coming out and correcting me this year.
Anyways, we should go and get started.
BSD is Dying.
What is BSD?
I think most of us know, BSD is a derivative of UNIX.
Okay, what is UNIX?
UNIX is an
operating system.
What is an operating system?
It runs computers.
But, what is a computer?
It helps users accomplish tasks. What is a user?
A user is somebody biped
that stands up right sort of like me.
Who am I? My name is Jason Dixon.
First and foremost, a SysAdmin. I like to work on networks,
firewalls. I like to tweak.
No. Yes.
I'm a programmer, sort of. I enjoy
Perl, Postgres,
on Apache
servers. I'm a consultant here. I'm an employee
here, and a lover of
BSD.
Why am I here?
That’s the question I've been asking myself all along.
To talk about why BSD is dying.
Sex and greed.
Someone kick these guys out.
Okay. So again, what is BSD? What is UNIX?
What is an operating system? What is a computer?
Computer is a device that computes, especially a
programmable electronic machine that performs high-speed
mathematical or logical operations or that assembles,
stores, correlates, or
otherwise processes
information.
This is a computer. This is also known as a
computer. This is a really big computer.
This is a big big computer, and sometimes,
it just can, well, compute
But what does a computer really do?
All right, it helps us write documents,
shopping lists. Sometimes, it can even delete documents.
It helps us work with email,
surf the Web, movies,
and listen to music.
Oh, and yes, games.
How? How does the computer let us do these
things? Well, it takes the work
and using the computer component, we can translate it
into machine language
that is the foundation
for kernel, libraries, userland applications,
otherwise known as an operating system.
like BSD.
What is a kernel?
It's a wonderful thing, it allows
The management of processes memory, peripheral devices,
and by extension, allows us to do networking, security,
work with disks and file systems, user interfaces,
userland applications, like
people can write documents, check email, surf the Web,
watch movies, listen to music, and play games.
and much, much more.
So, in summary, BSD
is a UNIX-derived operating system
enables users to harness the power of a computer to process
information. It uses the kernel to manage processes memory,
and peripheral devices. And by extension, we can perform
networking, enforce security, read from and write to storage
devices, and interface visually to applications like text
editors, mail clients, Web browsers, multimedia players, and
games.
In the beginning, I'm going to try and breeze through this,
people
The Holy
Trinity – MIT, Bell Labs, and GE created
a systems called Multics.
This is a nice flash from the past.
Life was good.
No. No.
Actually, it
wasn’t. The Multics was a commercial
failure. So, a couple of gentlemen like Ken Thompson and
Dennis Ritchie were not
[xx] support, liked to play games. They worked at Bell Labs
and they had this game called
Space Travel, which performed really
really badly. So, what's…actually, I'm sorry
it ran on a PDP-7.
What is an assembly programmer to do when a game
doesn’t work properly on the star board? He mauls
it. So, in 1969, Ken Thompson
and
Sorry, came out with the Uniplexed Information
and Computing System. It was capable of supporting
a number of users
up to two.
And by
1970, UNIX was officially known as U-N-I-X Unix
It ran on a PDP1145
and was capable of text processing
and had utilities like roff and a text editor.
for the purpose of
patents. By
1973, they rewrote UNIX and a programming language called
C which allowed AT&T to make the source code available
to let other
people run it on their systems.
By 1974, a gentleman by the name of Bob Fabry,
who was at the University
of Cal Berkeley in their Computer Science Department
bought a copy of UNIX for $99.
to run their PDP-11.
By 1977, a gentleman named Bill Joy, a graduate
student, distributed the Berkeley Software
Distribution as
1BSD. It was on a tape media that contained the PASCAL
compiler, the ex editor, and
by 1978, it was known as 2BSD with
vi, csh, and the list
goes on.
By 4BSD, we had job control, delivermail,
precursor to sendmail, curses, libraries. 1981,
4.1BSD, this one, we are recorded through VAX
addressed a number of memory performance issues with UNIX on VAX
1983, 4.2BSD uses TCP/IP from BBN,
and also the Berkeley Fast File System from the
gentleman, Kirk McKusick,
who also brought us the original Beastie today.
In 1986, 4.3BSD introduced performance improvements
over 4.2BSD
By 1988, we had a list called 4.3BSD-Tahoe
originally intended to run on the Power 6/32
“Tahoe” platform.
That platform actually never came to fruition
but it did allow us to abstract some of the
machine-independent
code which allowed it to become portable much later on.
By 1989, there was
Net/1, which separated the networking code
from the AT&T UNIX code
allowing for a permissive BSD license
By 1990, 4.3BSD-Reno
introduced the MACH virtual files, MACH virtual
memory system, Sun-compatible NFS
However, it was known as a real
gamble, hence the Reno moniker.
By 1991, we had
Net/2 where all AT&T code and utilities were
replaced or removed
and ran on the Intel 386
and it became the basis for the 386BSD
and BSD/386 releases.
A gentleman by the name of Bill Jolitz
behind 386
BSD release, which eventually became the foundation for
FreeBSD and NetBSD.
And the
BSD3, I'm sorry, the 386BSD, which later on became
BSD/OS by BSDI
Exodus. Back in 1992, a wholly owned subsidiary of
AT&T called Unix System Laboratories
decided to go after
BSDI for
I'm sorry,
in New
Jersey, as for an injunction against him due to various
what they consider proprietary
code in the
BSD.
This was one of their advertising things again, they used
this as the basis for the
lawsuit. I have
no idea what that’s for.
Net/2 was basically, I'm sorry
the three BSDIs version of BSD OS is basically Net/2
+ 6 files that they had version from
Bill Jolitz’s 386
BSD. The lawsuit was, I'm sorry, the court settlement was
ruled over by a judge who denied the injunction
and asked them to narrow their
complaint to recent California copyrights
and the possibility of the loss of
trade secrets. He also did a really great thing
for BSD is that he hinted,
that…actually by this
point, the University of California Berkeley had been
also added into the
lawsuit. Well, he gave a hint to bring the case to the state
court. So,
BSD laywers were pretty smart over at Cal and they decided
to make a run over to the state court by the next
Monday to file a countersuit
against USL,
in the state of California.
Soon after USL went up for
sale, and it was bought by Novell
A gentleman, Ray Noorda, the CEO
at Novell, agreed to a settlement at this point because
they understood that there was
no copyright infringement in the
code. So, basically,
the lawsuit was settled out of court
in secret for ten years.
In 2004, a site Groklaw primarily got
what the actual settlement
was released.
And, well
USL, AT&T and
Novell sort of
was embarrassed,
which ended up resulting in two distinct releases
4.4BSD, there is an encumbered version and had USL license
and AT&T code, and 4.4BSD-Lite, which was completely
unencumbered
and became the
foundation for
FreeBSD.
NetBSD, I'm sorry, FreeBSD, it ends right there
FreeBSD, people with background, only different BSDs
that came out of 386BSD
It runs on Intel x86, Itanium, AMD64, Alpha, Sun Ultra
SPARC and it gives us the neat features of jail, which
most of us are familiar with,
mandatory access control as MACH
and historically, had a very strong TCP/
IP and SMP performance.
The original NetBSD, which also came from 386BSD
Over 50 hardware platforms from a single
source tree
and that’s pretty much what it's known for. To be honest
I mean, I got to admit I'm an Open BSD guy, I was looking for
a really cool and innovative features for NetBSD and I really
couldn’t find any.
so let them hang their head on this.
Sorry,
I know people are going to…
I know the NetBSDers is going to jump me…I can
handle two of you. Okay? And this is
a list of the hardware platforms that currently supported on
including a toaster.
OpenBSD,
this is one of the old logos, this is the new
logo. It was forked from NetBSD 1.0, we won't go
into the history, I know
most people know it, and it's supported by about
16 official platforms
platforms. This is about half of the most popular ones.
And it comes out with a new release every six months,
generally, in May and November
1st, so if you haven’t already, pick a copy, that just came
out of the foil. It's unofficial model is secure by default
only what's needed is running on the default
And, some of their goals
and features - full disclosure, audits,
privsep, privilege separation & revocation, chroot jails,
like FreeBSD,
random values wherever possible. This is probably
the most obvious example. ProPolice
Some other features that they’d given us through
the years – PF, authpf, CARP, pfsyncd,
which I think some of these are probably in the
FreeBSD by now. DragonFlyBSD was a continuation of
FreeBSD 4.8. Again,
DragonFlyBSD was
forked with FreeBSD 4.8 and was intended to basically
overhaul the SMP features in FreeBSD 6
and 7..5,6, and 7.
DragonFly is another example. If you look at their goals,
it had some really neat technological stuff.
I can't find any features that really, you
know, mean anything.
Of course,
Tiger is an old I'm sorry, OSX
It started from the Jolitz project, but it's sort of an inbred
and then various others spearBSD, ecoBSD
and other minor BSDs
That is all about, I wanted to cover kind of the present of
where we are right now, some of the myths and truths.
Why is BSD dying? Really, that’s what the title
of the project and topic is.
Well, first, because IDC said so.
Market share for BSD is, right now, at an all time low, under 1%
And, of course, Netcraft confirms these findings.
Last place in the SysAdmin networking test, so we all
know that word, we're just big losers.
Because open-source projects are giving away free software.
I mean, we can't possibly make
money, so that, obviously, means that
we're dying. And free software is terrible
We know the insane let me get out.
Free software equals terrism.
Our inability to adapt. As you can see by this graph
Let's be serious here, people.
As per FreeBSD network pages per hour search
We see Windows, obviously I mean, they are way ahead people.
Come on, they’ve been doing this for a number of what? 15,
20 years. Linux is second.
They actually are showing some.
We presume that someone is doing authentication
by reading user pages
The BSD is only for register, so we've got to work
on that, of course
Loss of talent.
FreeBSD has lost 93% of their core developers.
Okay, come on, guys, let's go.
But not all is lost.
Fortunately, a few very small companies still
use BSD in this age.
I know you probably have heard most of these.
Believe it or not, this is our premier
sponsor, and some other company that didn’t sponsor us
I should just end right there.
because we're the nearest to them
Seriously, though, the technological challenge that we
have ahead of us. Virtualization, that’s a big deal
as far as the market.
Of course, developers are in the market, so,
if that happens, that
happens. Although the end is really, really cool.
DRM, is obviously evil, yes, I know, I don’t care about
DRM. Run Dell.
Right?
Political challenges
Now, this has been hard to entertain,
but I can't read this out in front of
people. Blobs,
binary is bad,
don’t do it
just smoke in the same crap
when it says
NDAs
and closed documentation.
How many of us here are actual core developers for
one of the BSDs?
Okay, the rest of us, let's help them
out
okay
get in touch with your supplier,
let's get some documentation to these guys.
Because without the
diversity, we have
unity
and a common goal.
Thank you.